<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Jean-Christophe Bélisle-Pipon</title>
    <link>https://BelislePipon.github.io/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Jean-Christophe Bélisle-Pipon</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Jean-Christophe Bélisle-Pipon</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/project/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Arts &#43; Bioethics</title>
      <link>https://BelislePipon.github.io/project/a&#43;b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://BelislePipon.github.io/project/a&#43;b/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How to engage the public in a reflection on the most pressing ethical issues of our time? What if part of the solution lies in adopting an interdisciplinary and collaborative strategy to shed light on critical issues in bioethics? An example is Arts+Bioéthique, an innovative project that brought together bioethicists, art historians and artists with the aim of expressing bioethics through arts in order to convey the “sensitive” aspect of many health ethics issues.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Direct-to-Consumer Communications</title>
      <link>https://BelislePipon.github.io/project/dtcc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://BelislePipon.github.io/project/dtcc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Direct-to-Consumer Communications include all forms of pharmaceutical industry-sponsored communications conveying promotional and informational content.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Public Health Ethics</title>
      <link>https://BelislePipon.github.io/project/phe/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://BelislePipon.github.io/project/phe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project focuses on the moral dimensions of public health. This includes ethics education, government transparency, expert conflict of interest, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several collaborators contributed to this project, including: Louise Ringuette, Victoria Doudenkova, Bryn Williams-Jones, Vardit Ravitsky, Olivier Bellefleur, Michael Keeling, Anne-Isabelle Cloutier.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
